<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="your_style.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>ADDRESS OF JOHN BROWN To the Virginia Court, when about to receive the SENTENCE OF
                DEATH, For his heroic attempt at Harper's Ferry, to Give deliverance to the captives,
                and to let the oppressed go free. </head>
            <p>[ Mr. Brown, upon inquiry whether he had anything to say why sentence should not be
                pronounced upon him, in a clear, distinct voice, replied:].</p> 
            <p>In the first place, I deny every thing but what 
                <seg ana="first-person">I have </seg> already admitted, of a design on my part to free Slaves. <seg ana="first-person">I
                intended </seg>, certainly, to have made a clean thing of that matter, as <seg ana="first-person">I did </seg> last winter, when
                I went into Missouri, and there took Slaves, without the snapping of a gun on either side,
                moving them through the country, and finally leaving them in Canada. I desired to have done
                the same thing again, on a much larger scale. That was all I intended. I never did intend
                murder, or treason, or the destruction of property, or to excite or incite Slaves to
                rebellion, or to make insurrection.</p>
            <p>I have another objection, and that is, that it is
            unjust that I should suffer such a penalty. Had I interfered in the manner, and which I
            admit has been fairly proved,—for I admire the truthfulness and candor of the greater
            portion of the witnesses who have testified in this case,—had I so interfered in behalf of
            the Rich, the Powerful, the Intelligent, the so-called Great, or in behalf of any of their
            friends, either father, mother, brother, sister, wife, or children, or any of that class,
            and suffered and sacrificed what I have in this interference, it would have been all right.
            Every man in this Court would have deemed it an act worthy a reward, rather than a
            punishment.</p>
            
           <p> This Court acknowledges too, as I suppose, the validity of the Law of God. I
            saw a book kissed, which I suppose to be the Bible, or at least the New Testament, which
            teaches me that, <quote>“All things whatsoever I would that men should do to me, I should do even
            so to them.” </quote>It teaches me further, to “Remember them that are in bonds, as bound with
            them.” I endeavored to act up to that instruction. I say I am yet too young to understand
            that God is any respecter of persons. I believe that to have interfered as I have done, as
            I have always freely admitted I have done, in behalf of his despised poor, I have done no
            wrong, but RIGHT.</p> 
            
            <p>Now, if it is deemed necessary that I should forfeit my life, for the
            furtherance of the ends of justice, and MINGLE MY BLOOD FURTHER WITH THE BLOOD OF MY
            CHILDREN, and with the blood of millions in this Slave country, whose rights are
            disregarded by wicked, cruel, and unjust enactments,—I say, LET IT BE DONE.</p>
            
            <p>Let me say one
            word further: I feel entirely satisfied with the treatment I have received on my trial.
            Considering all the circumstances, it has been more generous than I expected; but I feel no
            consciousness of guilt. <seg ana="first-person">I have stated </seg> from the first what was my intention, and what was
            not. I never had any design against the liberty of any person, nor any disposition to
            commit treason, or excite Slaves to rebel, or make any general insurrection. I never
            encouraged any man to do so, but always discouraged any idea of that kind.</p>
            
            <p> <seg ana="first-person">Let me say
                something, </seg>also, in regard to the statements made by some of those who were connected with
                me. I hear that it has been stated by some of them, that I have induced them to join me;
                but the contrary is true. I do not say this to injure them, but as regarding their
                weakness. Not one but joined me of his own accord, and the greater part at their own
                expense. A number of them I never saw and never had a word of conversation with, till the
                day they came to me, and that was for the purpose I have stated. Now I have done.</p>
            
           <byline> John
            Brown</byline>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
