<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="your_style.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>ADDRESS OF JOHN BROWN To the Virginia Court, when about to receive the SENTENCE OF
                DEATH, For his heroic attempt at Harper's Ferry, to Give deliverance to the captives,
                and to let the oppressed go free. </head>

            <p>[ Mr. Brown, upon inquiry whether he had anything to say why sentence should not be
                pronounced upon him, in a clear, distinct voice, replied:].</p> 

            <p>In the first place, I deny every thing but what 
                <seg ana="first-person">I have </seg> already admitted, of a design on my part to free Slaves. <seg ana="first-person">I
                intended </seg>, certainly, to have made a clean thing of that matter, as <seg ana="first-person">I did </seg> last winter, when
                <seg ana="first-person">I went </seg> into Missouri, and there took Slaves, without the snapping of a gun on either side,
                moving them through the country, and finally leaving them in Canada. <seg ana="first-person">I desired </seg> to have done
                the same thing again, on a much larger scale. That was all <seg ana="first-person">I intended </seg>. <seg ana="first-person">I never </seg> did intend
                murder, or treason, or the destruction of property, or to excite or incite Slaves to
                rebellion, or to make insurrection.</p>

            <p> <seg ana="first-person">I have </seg> another objection, and that is, that it is
            unjust that <seg ana="first-person">I should </seg> suffer such a penalty. Had <seg ana="first-person">I interfered </seg> in the manner, and which <seg ana="first-person">I
            admit </seg> has been fairly proved,—for <seg ana="first-person">I admire </seg> the truthfulness and candor of the greater
            portion of the witnesses who have testified in this case,—had <seg ana="first-person">I so interfered </seg> in behalf of
            the Rich, the Powerful, the Intelligent, the so-called Great, or in behalf of any of their
            friends, either father, mother, brother, sister, wife, or children, or any of that class,
            and suffered and sacrificed what <seg ana="first-person">I have </seg> in this interference, it would have been all right.
            Every man in this Court would have deemed it an act worthy a reward, rather than a
            punishment.</p>
            
           <p> This Court acknowledges too, as <seg ana="first-person">I suppose </seg>, the validity of the Law of God. <seg ana="first-person">I
            saw </seg> a book kissed, which <seg ana="first-person">I suppose </seg> to be the Bible, or at least the New Testament, which
            teaches me that, <quote>“All things whatsoever <seg ana="first-person"> I would </seg> that men should do to me, <seg ana="first-person">I should </seg> do even
            so to them.” </quote>It teaches me further, to “Remember them that are in bonds, as bound with
            them.” <seg ana="first-person">I endeavored </seg> to act up to that instruction. <seg ana="first-person">I say </seg> <seg ana="first-person">I am </seg> yet too young to understand
            that God is any respecter of persons. <seg ana="first-person">I believe </seg> that to have interfered as <seg ana="first-person">I have </seg> done, as
            <seg ana="first-person">I have </seg> always freely admitted <seg ana="first-person">I have </seg> done, in behalf of his despised poor, <seg ana="first-person">I have </seg> done no
            wrong, but RIGHT.</p> 
            
            <p>Now, if it is deemed necessary that <seg ana="first-person">I should </seg> forfeit my life, for the
            furtherance of the ends of justice, and MINGLE MY BLOOD FURTHER WITH THE BLOOD OF MY
            CHILDREN, and with the blood of millions in this Slave country, whose rights are
            disregarded by wicked, cruel, and unjust enactments,— <seg ana="first-person">I say </seg>, LET IT BE DONE.</p>
            
            <p>Let me say on word further: <seg ana="first-person">I feel </seg> entirely satisfied with the treatment <seg ana="first-person">I have </seg> received on my trial.
            Considering all the circumstances, it has been more generous than <seg ana="first-person">I expected </seg>; but <seg ana="first-person">I feel </seg> no
            consciousness of guilt. <seg ana="first-person">I have stated </seg> from the first what was my intention, and what was
            not. <seg ana="first-person">I never </seg> had any design against the liberty of any person, nor any disposition to
            commit treason, or excite Slaves to rebel, or make any general insurrection. <seg ana="first-person">I never </seg>
            encouraged any man to do so, but always discouraged any idea of that kind.</p>
            
            <p> <seg ana="first-person">Let me say
                something, </seg> also, in regard to the statements made by some of those who were connected with
                me. <seg ana="first-person">I hear </seg> that it has been stated by some of them, that <seg ana="first-person">I have </seg> induced them to join me;
                but the contrary is true. <seg ana="first-person">I do </seg> not say this to injure them, but as regarding their
                weakness. Not one but joined me of his own accord, and the greater part at their own
                expense. A number of them <seg ana="first-person">I never </seg> saw and never had a word of conversation with, till the
                day they came to me, and that was for the purpose <seg ana="first-person">I have </seg> stated. Now <seg ana="first-person">I have </seg> done.</p>
            
           <byline> John
            Brown</byline>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
Barbara Twyman
TEI Coding Explanations  
12/06/2017

</p> I used the code <p> because it was the beginning of what I saw as each paragraph.

</head> I used the code <p> because for me it stated what the affirmation of the plea was about. He was begging for his life and was about to receive the death penalty for his heroic attempt to help free people who were oppressed. 

<seg ana="first-person"> I used the code </seg> because it showed personal responsibility and accountability for everything that lead up to the events in question. This to me was the most important code because he wasn’t blaming anyone else John Brown let them know that he solely acted alone. That is the most powerful thing a person under these circumstances can do. 

<quote> I used the code </quote> because I thought that this was the most import quote of all. In this quote John Brown explains that what brought him to this point was that he did unto other as they did unto him. This was the most powerful quote in the whole speech. 
